نسينا
Have we forgotten
اني بأرضي وهاي بلادي
That I'm in my land, and this is my country
و فبلادي سجين
And in my country, I’m imprisoned?
فبلادي سجين
In my country, I’m imprisoned
فيها
And here
تراب اليوم نسقيه بدموع
We water it’s soil with tears
ودم شهيد
And the blood of its defenders
دم شهيد
The blood of its defenders
فيها قصة مكتوبة نصر
Here our story and victory is written
بلادنا النا من البحر للنهر
Our country is ours, from sea to river
ياما قلنا بكرا احلى
Often we say tomorrow will be better
بس لا ما شفنا الا قهر
But only ever see oppression
طلبنا بس حرية نعيش
All we asked for was the freedom to live
شفنا بس قتل وتهجير
But all we got in return was death and displacement
حتى نحكي لا ممنوع
Not even a spoken word is allowed
سجن حدود وسجن بتعبير
It’s a prison of borders and silenced expression
وذنبه ايه طفل الشهيد
What crime did the murdered child commit
كان حلمه مستقبل زهيد
Who dreamt of only a modest future?
والي عايش طفل تاني
And what of the child who survived
بس أهله ميتين
Only to lose their family
ما نسينا
We haven’t forgotten
وبلي صاير فينا
What’s happening to us
على ترابك ماتخلينا
You never abandoned us on your soil
ودم الشهيد فداك يا وطني
And the blood of our defenders is a sacrifice for you, oh my homeland
تبلينا وراح إلي مواسينا
We suffered, and those who used to console us have gone
وشكون إلي بينا
Who is left among us?
والله متوحش ناسي إلي جواتني
I swear, I terribly miss the people who used to stand with me
كل يوم
And every day
بحكولي صبري سلاحي
They tell me my patience is my weapon
واخر صبري الموت
While our timer ticks towards death
والكل شايف  بس لا  مش فارق
While everyone watches, But no, it doesn’t matter
صوتي حياه
My voice is life
وانا واقف وحدي
And I stand alone
العالم ضدي
The world against me
وانا ما اخشاه
And I don’t fear it
سلبوني روحي حتى الارض تعيش
They take my soul only to take my soil
مفتاح البيت بقلبي
But the key to my home remains in my heart
وانا راجع وبايدي ولدي
And I'm returning with my children in my arms
ولو كل العالم كان ضدي
Even if the whole world stands against me
انا راجع يا بلادي
I am returning, O my country
راجع
I am returning!
مفتاح البيت بقلبي
The key to my home remains in my heart
وانا راجع وبايدي ولدي
And I'm returning with my children in my arms
ولو كل العالم كان ضدي
Even if the whole world stands against me
انا راجع يا بلادي
I am returning, O my country
راجع
I am returning!
وين حكام العالم وين القادة؟
We call on you Arab leaders
اخواتي في غزة اليوم تتعرض للإبادة
Our families in Gaza today are subject to extermination
هما كلمتين: اما النصر اما الشهادة
We’re given two choices: either death or victory
فلسطيني شهيد منذ تاريخ الولادة
A Palestinian - condemned to death since birth!
وصبرا جميلاً، العدو سيزول
But be patient, those against us will not prevail
وين الأمة العربية؟حان الوقت لنثور
Where are the Arab communities? It’s time to rise up
كيف يبان وعد الحق، يوفا وعد بلفور
How can we declare peace, When Belfour’s declaration stands?
و انا قلبي فلسطيني à la vie à la mort
Still my heart is Palestinian, in life, in death
كل الدنيا بلادي وارضي
All the world is my country
في كل مكان
far and wide
كل الدنيا بلادي
All people are my brethren
من قديم الزمان
since the days of old
الفروق بينا حدود
Borders are the differences between us
كلام عالورد مكتوب
And words are written on roses
والمكتوب اصبح قيود
And what was written has become a chain
تمنعنا نشوف، بلاد
Denying me from seeing my country
قتلونا و هجرونا و صار الحجر بايدي سلاحي
They killed us, they displaced us, and now the stones in our hands are our weapons
متلثم ابيض و اسود كوفيتي هي سر نجاحي
Checkered in black and white, my Kufiya is the secret of my success
وبكفي كفني شايل و بكفك كر اللي جاي
In my hand, I carry my coffin, and in your hand, you carry revenge
مفتاح البيت عَرقبتي سدادة ما بتمايل
The key to my home hangs on my neck, eternal and never swaying
مفتاح البيت بقلبي
But the key to my home remains in my heart
وانا راجع وبايدي ولدي
And I'm returning with my children in my arms
ولو كل العالم كان ضدي
Even if the whole world stands against me
انا راجع يا بلادي راجع
I am returning, O my country, I am returning
مفتاح البيت بقلبي
But the key to my home remains in my heart
وانا راجع وبايدي ولدي
And I'm returning with my children in my arms
ولو كل العالم كان ضدي
Even if the whole world stands against me
انا راجع يا بلادي راجع
I am returning, O my country, I am returning
إلاهي رفعت يدي اليك
O Lord, I raise my hands to You
بأن تفك كربي و همي و انت المستجيب
I ask You to relieve my agony and my sorrow, and You are the Responsive One
بلاد العرب اوطاني
The lands of the Arabs are my homelands
من الشام لبغداني
From the Levant to Baghdad
ارضي هي وبلادي
This is my land and my country
وكل العرب بتنادي
And all the Arabs are calling out
احتلالي عدواني
My occupation is violent
موت طفلي واجدادي
Killing my children and ancestors
اسألني مين ارهابي
You keep calling me a terrorist
وجاي اقلك مين بادي
I ask you if you’re an occupier
سوري اني مش من اوكرانيا
Sorry that I'm not from Ukraine
سوري انه بشرتي مش بيضه
Sorry that my skin is not white
سوري لولادي سوري اني جبتكم على دنيا منافقه ومش عادله
Sorry to my children, that I brought you into a hypocritical and unfair world
سوري الحلم طويل يابا
Sorry, the dream is far away, my son
سوري الحمل ثقيل يابا
Sorry, the burden is heavy, my son
لا سوري على اي سوري
No sorry for all the “sorries”
ملناش غير أنه نشيل يابا
We have nothing but to endure, my son
هنا الموت حاجة سهله بس صعبه الحياه
Here, death is easy but living is hard
حريه كذابه عالم استبدادي
A false freedom in a world of tyranny
ما نستقبل ضيوف نستقبل شهداء
We don’t receive guests, we receive our death
ما نسينا الدُره وقصف المعمداني
We haven’t forgotten Al-Durrah and the bombing of The Baptist Hospital
إباده جماعيه أطفال و نساء
Mass destruction, children and women
يموت عزيز ما نبكي دا شهيد
As our dear ones die, we don’t cry, it’s for the cause
نصره نصره وتبقى العزه لله
Victory, victory, and only God is the Almighty
راجعين ي اقصى ووعد الله اكيد
We will return, oh Al-Aqsa, for His promise is certain
الله
By God
ماكو تهجير
No displacement!
جبل ثابت ما نَهاب التفجير
We’re a standing mountain that fears no bombardment!
يا غزاة: انتصارنا قادم اكيد
Oh Gazans, our victory is coming for sure!
بصمودي قاهر ذاك الخبيث
Our resilience will overcome this sinister occupation!
بالمشاعر بَليد .. ما شاف أحد من عياله شهيد
No empathy for us – even while our children are dead in our streets
أرواحهم أمانة بأرقاب الجميع .. أمانة شريف
The childrens’ souls are entrusted for us to honor... a noble trust
فـ بنواصل ندافع نموت لبقاء فلسطين!
So, we continue to defend, we will die so Palestine can remain!
لي طاري ابشع و ابشع منو تخون
(الذي يحدث قبيح واقبح ان تخون)
What’s happening is horrible, and selling out is even worse
گاع لي كايقول الصراحة كايقطعو لو الصوت
(اي واحد يقول الحقيقة يقطع صوته)
And all who speak up are silenced
بنادم ولا خايف يدوي لايحيدولو الكونط
(الناس امتنعت عن الكلام خوفا من حذف حساباتها)
People hold their tongue for fear of losing their platform
اخي راه الدم فاير و القلب مشوط
(اخي ان الدم ثائر و القلب محروق)
My brother, my blood boils, and my heart burns
راه مقدراتش عيني تشوف داكشي لي وصور
(لم تستطع عيني ان ترى ماهو مصور)
My eyes can’t bear to see the images they’re seeing
الشيطان جالس فالعرش و اللي معاه كايصوت
(الشيطان جالس في العرش و من معه يصوت لصالحه)
A devil sits on a throne and his minions protect him
ف ٤٦ دخل السرطان
In ‘48, death came into Palestine
٧٥ عام تحت الرصاص
75 years of bombing
لا مشا جيل جاي الفيضان
(اذا ذهب جيل سيعود الفيضان)
But even if a generation leaves, we will flood back
قلبي نضيف و ما يصفا
My heart is pure but won’t find peace
حتي ناخذ بثار المستشفى
Until we find justice for the hospital
ضلم و صار بالكشفا
Injustice has become blatant
وين الرجال القلوب ناشفة
Where are the men? Our are hearts are parched
صاحبي مهما الدنيا تقسى زادت النكسة الظلم فايت حدو الاقصى
My friend, no matter how harsh the world gets, and the oppression has reached its breaking point
سلامي لغزة مش ناقصة
We send peace to Gaza, never forgotten
انشاء الله نتقابلو في الاقصى
God willing, we will meet in Al-Aqsa
والارض هاي لينا
And this land is ours
لو فوق الارض او تحتيها
Whether we're above the land or beneath it
ساقاوم و جمع تلاقينا
We’ll resist, united in numbers
بطوفاني اجول و احميها
I am a hurricane, I roam and protect it
والاقصى لينا
And Al-Aqsa is ours
لو يقصي عدوي اساميها
Even if my enemy erases its name
لو أقسى الناس تعادينا
Even if the most vicious of people oppose us
وانا راجع يا بلادي راجع
I am returning, O my country, I am returning
ليس لنا عوناً سواه
We have no hope but Him
ارسل لنا ربي خلاص
Our Lord, deliver unto us salvation
في روحنا جهد ثقال
Our souls are heavy and weary
في قلوبنا بلد وثأر
In our hearts, a nation erupts
وبروحنا وقلوبنا
And with the strength in my heart and soul…
راجع تاني علي ارضي
I’m returning again to my land
الاقصى اصلي فيه فرضي
Al-Aqsa is where I will hold my next prayer
جاية معاكو بطياران؟
Come at me with your planes?
انا زميلي جي معاكو ارضي
I’m waiting for you on the land
فدائي .. فدائي ..فدائي
My redemption, My redemption, My redemption
انا مش ماشي انا في مكاني
I’m not leaving; I’m rooted here
علي خط النار كل ليل ونهار ولو هموت وفي ايدي سلاحي
On the frontline, every night and day, even if I have to die for my country.
حد الما يجي النسيم
Until the breeze comes
ورا الزاي نجيب
How can we back down?
احنا فصف العزيز
We are in the rank of the Mighty One
سامحنا يا رحيم اننا عاجزين عمره ما كان تطبيع
Forgive us, O Merciful, for our helplessness, but we have never normalized
شفنا السفاحين
We saw the butchers
تقتل طفل بريء
Slaughtering the innocent child
فدمه تستبيح
Sanctioning his blood
زيفوا التاريخ بدموع التماسيح
As they falsify history with crocodile tears
سحقاً لقاتلي الأطفال
Condemn the killers of children
صانعي الأهوال
Makers of terror
كاذبي الأقول
Purveyors of lies
سارقي الأمال
Thieves of hope
أطفالنا في الجنان عايشين
Our children live in paradise
بلدنا ومنها ما ماشين
This is our land and we shall not leave
أرضنا وفيها مزروعين
Our land, in which we are planted
عزل بدون سلاح لاكين
Isolated without weapons, however
معانا رب العالمين
With us is the Almighty
(ملناش غير رب العالمين)
(Our only refuge is the Almighty)
لو رحل صوتي ما بترحل حناجركم
Should I lose my voice, yours will remain...
الترجمة الفرعية: زبير بن ضمير (بنغلاديش)
Subtitle by: Zubair Ibn Zamir (Bangladesh)
www.zubairiz.com - www.zmt3.com